Guide to the Raymond Hood Photograph Collection 1911-1933 PR 148
New-York Historical Society
Raymond Hood Photograph Collection
1911-1933
New-York Historical Society
PR 148
8.04 Linear feet (6 boxes)
The Raymond Hood Photograph Collection spans the years 1911-1913 and primarily contains photographs of buildings designed by architect Raymond Hood. Buildings pictured are: the Daily News building, the McGraw-Hill building, the American Radiator Company building, all in New York City, the Chicago Tribune Building, and the National Radiator building in London. Photographs of private homes, apartment buildings, churches, memorials, World's Fair exhibits, and competition drawings are also included.
Provenance
Gift of Harrison & Abramovitz, July 10, 1950.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Raymond Mathewson Hood (1881-1934) was born in Rhode Island and attended Brown University, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and the Ecole des Beaux Arts in Paris, where he studied architecture and design. Hood returned to the United States and established an independent architectural practice in New York in 1914. He entered architectural competitions and took an industrial design job designing radiator covers for the American Radiator Company.
In 1922 Hood, in partnership with the architect John Mead Howells, won the design competition for the new Chicago Tribune Building. This prestigious assignment led to more commissions for large office buildings, such as the American Radiator Company Building, the Daily News Building, and the McGraw-Hill Building, all in New York City. In addition to large office towers, Hood designed apartment buildings, single-family residences, memorials, churches, tombs, and college dormitories. He worked under his own name and also in partnership with Howells, as well as with engineer J. Andre Fouilhoux, and architect Frederick Godley.
Hood also contributed designs for Rockefeller Center, but died before the project came to completion. Hood often used the Art Deco style and collaborated with artists to create murals and sculptures that set his designs apart from other architects. Hood served as president of the Architectural League of New York from 1929 to 1931 and received its Medal of Honor in 1926.
Scope and Content Note
The Raymond Hood Photograph Collection spans the period from 1911-1933 and primarily contains photographs of buildings designed by architect Raymond Hood. During his career, Hood worked in partnerships with other architects, including the firms of Godley, Fouilhoux, and Barber; Hood & Howells; Hood & Fouilhoux; Hood, Godley & Fouilhoux; and Hood & Murchison. Hood's work with all these firms is included in this collection. The projects were designed for the United States, except for one building built in London, England. The collection is divided into four series: Completed Structures; Competition Designs and Plans; Exhibitions; and Other.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series:
Missing Title
Series I. Completed Structures
Series II. Competition Designs and Plans
Series III. Exhibitions
Series IV. Other
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
This collection was removed from the Architect and Engineer File (PR-003) in 2002. Photographs of work done solely by John Mead Howells is included in that File (PR-003-215). Hood's architectural drawings are held by Columbia University's Avery Library.
Architectural drawings (visual works); Chicago (Ill.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; Skyscrapers -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Office buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Dwellings -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Photographic prints.; Commercial buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; Church buildings -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Architecture -- United States -- 20th century -- Designs and plans.; Architecture -- Competitions -- United States.; Apartment houses -- United States -- Pictorial works.; American Radiator Company -- Buildings.; Daily News Building (New York, N.Y.); Hood & Howells; Howells, John Mead, 1868-1959; McGraw-Hill Publishing Company -- Buildings.; National Radiator Company -- Buildings.; Raymond Hood, Godley & Fouilhoux; Rotan, Thurman, 1903-1991; Tribune Tower (Chicago, Ill.)
- Series I: Completed Structures
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. includes both interior and exterior photographs of structures designed by Raymond Hood. Within this series, structures are arranged alphabetically by state and city and thereunder are filed by date. A few tombs, mausoleums, and memorials are included in this series, but the majority of the structures are office buildings and private homes. Three of Hood's major projects, the Daily News Building and the American Radiator Building, both in New York City, and the Chicago Tribune Tower, are well-represented. Some images of the Daily News Building were taken by New York photographer Thurman Rotan (1903-1991). In most other cases the photographer is not known.
  Interior and exterior views of four Rex Cole showrooms in Brooklyn and Queens are included here. Rex Cole was a refrigerator distributor, and Hood designed free-standing buildings to showcase the new lines of household appliances.
  In addition to the Daily News Building, Hood designed two homes for Colonel Joseph Medill Patterson, the paper's publisher. Patterson's large home in Ossining, New York included a rooftop observatory. Hood also designed a small apartment building in Manhattan for Patterson. Other residences included in this series include the Manhattan townhouse of John Green, the luxurious Beaux Arts Apartments, and Hood's own home in Stamford, Connecticut.
  The collection contains no photographs of Rockefeller Center.
  The series is arranged based on geographical location, and thereunder by date.
  - Connecticut--Greenwich
    - Morris residence, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Connecticut--Stamford
    - Hood residence, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Delaware--Wilmington
    - Hotel Dupont additions, 1911, 1913, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Illinois--Chicago
    - Chicago Tribune Tower--Competition designs and plans, 1922-1925 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chicago Tribune Tower--Exterior views, 1922-1925 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
    - Chicago Tribune Tower--Interior views, 1922-1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Thomason tomb, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Bethany Union Church, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Illinois--Rockford
    - Medill McCormick mausoleum, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - New Jersey--Montclair
    - Soldier's Memorial, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - New York--New York City--Brooklyn
    - Rex Cole showrooms [Bay Ridge], 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - New York--New York City--Manhattan
    - Mori's Restaurant, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - John Green residence, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - American Radiator Building--Exterior views, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - American Radiator Building--Interior views, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - American Radiator Building--Ephemera, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - NBC Studios, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Patterson apartment building, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Daily News Building--Exterior views, 1929-1930 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
    - Daily News Building--Interior views, 1929-1930 (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
    - Beaux Arts Apartments, 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - McGraw-Hill Building, 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - New York--New York City--Queens
    - Rex Cole showrooms [Flushing], 1929-1933 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - New York--Ossining
    - Patterson residence--Exterior views, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Patterson residence--Interior views, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - New York--Sands Point
    - Brooks residence [includes portfolio], 1933 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - New York--Tarrytown
    - St. Vincent de Paul Asylum, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Pennsylvania--Scranton
    - Masonic Temple and Scottish Rite Cathedral [includes portfolio], 1926-1929 (Box 5, Folder 31-32)
  - Tennessee--Nashville
    - George Peabody Collegge for Teachers building, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - England--London
    - National Radiator Building [Ideal House], 1928 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Series II: Competition Designs and Plans
  Series II. includes photographs and photostats of drawings submitted by Hood to various architectural competitions. Any drawings or plans for buildings that were completed are housed in Series I along with photographs of the completed buildings. Included here are a plan for a resort community in South Carolina, a plan for a Methodist National Cathedral, designs for an ocean liner, two courthouses and a town hall, and two speculative projects envisioning future high-rise development in New York City.
  The series is arranged by geographical location, and thereunder by date.
  - New Jersey--Ridgewood
    - Ridgewood Municipal Buildng [Town Hall], 1926 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - New York--Dobbs Ferry
    - Country Tower, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - New York--New York City
    - City of Towers, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Manhattan 1950, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - New York--Rockland County
    - Rockland County Courthouse, 1928 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Ohio--Columbus
    - Methodist National Cathedral, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Pennsylvania--Philadelphia
    - Girard College Chapel, 1930 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - South Carolina--Myrtle Beach
    - Arcady, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Wisconsin--Milwaukee
    - Milwaukee County Courthouse, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Unidentified Location
    - Academy of Music, 1920 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - USA Lines ocean liner, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 45)
- Series III: Exhibitions
  Series III. Exhibitions contains images from the 11th annual American Industrial Art Exhibition, held in the Metropolitan Museum of Art in 1929, and A Century of Progress Exhibition, the Chicago World's Fair of 1933-1934. For the former, Hood designed a business executive's office and an apartment house loggia. For the Chicago World's Fair, Hood designed the Electrical Building Pavilion, as well as an exhibition garden for the American Radiator Company, and an exhibit for General Electric. Photographs of all these are found in this series.
  The series is arranged chronologically.
  - American Industrial Art Exhibition
    - American Industrial Art Exhibition, 1929 Feb.-Sep. (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - A Century of Progress Exhibition
    - American Radiator exhibition garden, 1929-1933 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Electrical Building design, 1929-1933 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - General Electric exhibit, 1929-1933 (Box 6, Folder 49)
- Series IV: Other
  Series IV. Other includes several photographs of a frieze from a Hood building that could not be identified, as well as views of buildings designed by other architects, such as the Roerich Museum, and a few miscellaneous photographs, including an aerial view of Manhattan and a group portrait of the Chicago chapter of the American Institute of Architects.
  - Unidentified buildings deisgned by Hood, undated (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Buildings not designed by Hood, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)